Guide to the Eugène and Maria Jolas Papers: Addition
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Eugène and Maria Jolas papers: addition
1932-1986
GEN MSS 411
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.8
(3 boxes)
This addition to the Eugène and Maria Jolas Papers consists of items which were separated from the printed component of the collection of Eugène and Maria Jolas when the books and serials were cataloged in 1998. The addition consists of letters, clippings, offprints, and other printed items.
Jolas, Eugène, 1894-1952
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were removed from the printed component of the Eugène and Maria Jolas papers, which were acquired by gift and purchase from Betsy and Tina Jolas in 1989.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Associated Materials
Eugène and Maria Jolas Papers, GEN MSS 108
EUGÈNE AND MARIA JOLAS
Eugène Jolas (1894-1952), poet, journalist and translator, was the founding editor (with Elliot Paul) of transition. Maria Jolas (1893-1987), his wife, was a translator in her own right, as well as a school administrator and, along with Eugène, a confidant of James Joyce. More complete biographical sketches can be found in the finding aid for the Eugène and Maria Jolas Papers (GEN MSS 108).
Scope and Contents
This addition to the Eugène and Maria Jolas Papers consists of items which were separated from the printed component of the collection of Eugène and Maria Jolas when the books and serials were cataloged in 1998.
Series I, Items removed from printed works (ca. 1945-86), contains: drafts of writings by Maria Jolas; pieces of correspondence, mainly to Maria Jola from persons such as Allen Binstock and Noam Chomsky; notes by Maria Jolas (usually concerning the book from which the note was removed); clippings; and other items. Series II, Offprints (1932-85), contains writings on a variety of subjects, mostly by persons Maria Jolas knew personally. Series III, Other Printed Items (1938-79), contains issues of journals, an invitation, and a photograph of Lucia Joyce's grave.
Authors, French -- 20th Century -- Archives; Modernism (Literature); Paris (France) -- Intellectual life; Authors; Jolas, Eugène, 1894-1952; Jolas, M.; Joyce, James, 1882-1941
- Items removed from printed works, 1932-85; Series I; 0.2; (1 box)
  - Writings by Maria Jolas
    - "L'Affaire Rimbaud: Who wrote 'La chasse spirituelle'?", typescript carbon, corrected, ca. 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      Removed from: La Chasse Spirituelle, Mercure de France, 1949
    - Essay on James Joyce and Eugène Jolas, printed version (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Removed from: Marvin Magalaner and Richard M. Kain, Joyce, the man, the work, the reputation, N.Y. Univ. Press, 1956.
    - Translation of "The Age of Suspicion" by Nathalie Sarraute, printed version [in Envoy ], corrected, with notes, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence
    - Binstock, Allen to Maria Jolas, 1974-75 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Also includes: draft of reply from Maria Jolas to Binstock, 1975 Nov 14
      Removed from: Cornelius Castoriadis, Institution imaginaire de la société, Editions de Seuil, 1975
    - Castoriadis, Cornelius to Maria Jolas, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Also includes: copies of letters from Castoriadis to Noam Chomsky, André Schiffrin, and Allen Binstock, 1975 Jul 19
    - Chomsky, Noam to Maria Jolas, 1974 Aug 6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Removed from: Cornelius Castoriadis, Institution imaginaire de la societe, Editions de Seuil, 1975
    - Freund, Gisele to Maria Jolas, 1986 May 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Removed from: Gisele Freund, Three days with Joyce, Persea Books, 1985
    - Jolas, Maria to the editor of Phoenix, 1972 Feb 26 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Also includes: Letter from Maria Jolas to M. S. Arnoni, 1972 Mar, letter from Susan Huey of The Beacon Press to Maria Jolas, 1972 Feb 4, and clippings regarding The French Student Uprising, 1972
      Removed from: Pierre Vidal-Naquet, The French Student Uprising, Beacon Press, 1972
    - Jolas, Maria to André Schiffrin, 1974 Oct 6 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Le Brocquy, Louis to Maria Jolas, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Removed from: Louis Le Brocquy, Studies toward an image of James Joyce, S. Marco dei Giustiniani, 1978
    - McCarville, Eileen to Maria Jolas, 1977 Jun 16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Removed from: Robert Scholes and Richard M. Cain, eds. Workshop of Daedalus, Northwestern Univ. Press, 1965
    - Thomas Jefferson Memorial Foundation to Ann-Marie Toll, 1981 Jun 21 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Removed from: Samuel W. Thomas, ed., Views of Louisville since 1766, Courier-Journal/Louisville Times, 1971
  - Notes by Maria Jolas
    - Removed from: M. M. Austin and Pierre Vidal-Naquet, Economic and Social History of Ancient Greece, B. T. Batsford, Inc., 1977, ca. 1977 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Removed from: Cornelius Castoriadis, Institution imaginaire de la societe, Editions de Seuil, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Removed from: Rene Char, Aromates chasseurs, Editions Gallimard, 1975, ca. 1975 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Removed from: Noel Riley Fitch, Sylvia Beach and the Lost Generation, W. W. Norton, 1983, ca. 1983 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Also includes: clippings and card presenting book from the Gotham Book Mart
    - Removed from: Flavius Josephus, Guerre des Juifs, Editions de minuit, 1977, ca. 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Removed from: Richard Ellmann, ed. Letters of James Joyce, Faber and Faber, 1966, ca. 1966 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Removed from: Richard Ellmann, ed. Selected letters of James Joyce, Faber and Faber, 1975, ca. 1975 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Also includes: clipping, 1979
    - Removed from James Joyce, Portrait of the Artist as a Young Man, Continental Book Company, 1945, ca. 1945 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Removed from: Stanislaus Joyce, My Brother's Keeper, Viking Press, 1958, ca. 1958 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Removed from: Jane Lidderdale, Dear Miss Weaver, Viking Press, 1970, ca. 1970 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Removed from: Nathalie Sarraute, Between Life and Death, George Braziller, 1969, ca. 1969 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Removed from: Nathalie Sarraute, Collected Plays, John Calder, 1980, ca. 1980 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Removed from: Nathalie Sarraute, Fruits d'or, Gallimard, 1963, ca. 1963 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Removed from: Nathalie Sarraute, Théâtre, Gallimard, 1978, ca. 1978 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Removed from: Nathalie Sarraute, Tropismes, Editions de minuit, 1957, ca. 1957 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Removed from: Kate Traumann Steinitz, Kurt Schwitters, Univ. of California Press, 1968, ca. 1969 (Box 1, Folder 28)
      Also includes: invitation to reception for Kate Steinitz, 1969
  - Notes by Pierre Vidal-Naquet
    - Removed from: Elias Petropoulos, Macabre Song, 1985, ca. 1985 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Clippings
    - in re: Maria Jolas and Eugène Jolas obituary, 1952, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Removed from: Arizona Quarterly, vol. 19, number 2, SUmmer 1963
    - in re: Finnegans Wake, 1982 Dec 10 (Box 1, Folder 31)
      Removed from: James Joyce, Finnegans Wake [French], Gallimard, 1982
    - in re: "Ulysses in Nighttown", 1959 Jul 10 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Removed from: Marvin Magalaner, ed., James Joyce Miscellany, Southern Ill. Univ. Press, 1959
    - in re: James Joyce, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 33)
      Removed from: James Joyce e la primera versione italiana del Finnegans Wake, Cavallino, 1955
    - in re: Pierre Vidal-Naquet, 1977 Jul 11 (Box 1, Folder 34)
      Removed from: Flavius Josephe ou du bon usage de la trahison, Editions de minuit, 1977
    - in re: Ahmed Ben Bella, 1972 Jul (Box 1, Folder 35)
      Removed from: Pierre Vidal-Naquet, Torture dans la république, Editions de minuit, 1972
  - Other items
    - Concert announcement for Robert Soëtens, 1952 Jun 11 (Box 1, Folder 36)
      Removed from: Kathleen Raine and Max-Pol Fouchet, Aspects de la littérature anglaise, Fontaine, 1947
    - Announcement of and invitation to Samuel Beckett play, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 37)
      Also includes: presentation card from publisher
      Removed from: Beckett at 60: A Festschrift, Calder and Boyars, 1967
    - Photocopies of vocabulary terms and blank postcard, 1958, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 38)
      Removed from: Robert Jaulin, Le Mort sara, Plon, 1967
    - Issue of Le Point, 1972 Oct 2 (Box 1, Folder 39)
      Removed from: James Joyce, Essais critiques, Gallimard, 1966
    - Advertisement for Adrienne Monnier's Dernières gazettes et écrits divers, Mercure de France, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 40)
      Removed from: [same]
- Offprints, 1932-85; Series II; 0.2; (1 box)
  - Day, Robert Adams, "Joyce's Gnomons, Lenehan, and the Persistance of an Image", offprint from Novel, A Forum on Fiction, 1980 Fall (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Edel, Leon, "Henry James: The War Chapter, 1914-1916", offprint from The University of Toronto Quarterly, 1941 Jan
  - Ellmann, Richard
    - "The Art of Yeats: Affirmative Capability", offprint from The Kenyon Review, 1953 Summer
    - "The Backgrounds of 'The Dead'", offprint from The Kenyon Review, 1958 Autumn
  - Goll, Iwan, "Ein Tag aus dem Leben eines Genies", offprint, 1932 Jul
  - Grossman, D. Jon, "Un poète international: Eugène Jolas", offprint from Critique: Revue générale des publications françaises et étrangères, 1952 Jul
  - Haupt, Georges and Jolyon Howorth, "Edouard Vaillant, délégué au Bureau socialiste international: correspondance avec le Secrétariat international (1900-1915)", offprint from Annali della Fondazione Giangiacomo Feltrinelli, 1976
  - Howard, Dick, "Esprit", offprint from Telos, 1978 Summer
  - Jolas, Maria
    - "L'élegant chemin de James Joyce" offprint from Lettres Nouvelles (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - "J'écris, dit Joyce", offprint from Joyce & Paris, 1979
    - "The Little Known Paul Leon", offprint from A James Joyce Miscellany, n.d.
  - Kain, Richard, "He Who Runes May Rede..: Joyce as Philologist", offprint from Mosaic, 1969 Winter (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Levin, Harry, "The Title as a Literary Genre", offprint from The Modern Language Review, 1977 Oct
  - Leon, Paul, "Les idées sociales et politiques du Guild-Socialism", offprint from Archives de Philosophie du droit et de Sociologie juridique, 1931
  - Loraux, Nicole
    - "L'Autochthonie: une topique athénienne" offprint from Annales: Economies, Societes, Civilisations, 1979 Jan-Feb (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - "Aux origines de la démocratie", offprint from Raison Présente, 1979
    - "Mourir devant Troie, tomber pour Athènes: De la gloire du héros à l'idée de la cité", offprint from Information sur les sciences sociales, 1978
    - "Socrate Contrepoison de l'oraison funèbre", offprint from L'Antiquité Classique, 1974
    - "Sur la race des femmes et quelques- unes de ses tribus", offprint from Arethusa, 1978
  - Marienstras, Elise, "Problèmes d' historiographie américaine: Le champ amérindien", offprint from Annales: Economies, Societes, Civilisations, 1978 Mar-Apr (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Mayoux, Jean-Jacques, "At the Sources of Symbolism", offprint from Criticism: a Quarterly for Literature and the Arts, 1959 Fall
  - Spoerri, James, "The Odyssey Press Edition of James Joyce's 'Ulysses'", offprint from The Papers of the Bibliographical Society of America, 1956
  - Vidal-Naquet, Pierre
    - "Les boucliers des héros", offprint from Annali del Seminario di Studi del Mondo Classico, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 46-47)
    - with Loraux, Nicole, [entries for Dictionnaire des Mythologies ], offprints, 1980
    - "Esclavage et gynécocratie dans la tradition, le mythe, l'utopie", offprint, n.d.
    - "Les esclaves immortelles d'athéna Ilias", offprint from Le Monde Grec, 1975
    - "Une fidélité têtue: La résistance française à la guerre d'Algérie", Université de Turku, 1985
    - "Flavius Josèphe et Masada", offprint from Revuew historique, 1978
    - with Loraux, Nicole, "La formation de l'Athènes bourgeoise", offprint from Classical Influences on Western Thought A.D. 1650-1870, 1978
    - "Les Jeunes: Le cru, l'enfant grec et le cuit", offprint from Faire de l'histoire, n.d.
    - "Langue et histoire ou le dilemme des origines grecques", offprint from Raison Présente, n.d.
    - with Jacques le Goff, "Lévi-Strauss en Brocéliande", offprint from Critique, 1974 Jun
    - "Le mythe platonicien du 'Politique', les ambiguïtés de l'âge d'or et de l'histoire", offprint from Langue, Discours, Societé, Pour Emile Benveniste, 1975
    - "Oedipe à Vicence et à Paris" offprint from Quaderni di storia, 1981 Dec
    - "Le Philoctète de Sophocle et l'éphébie" offprint from Annales: Économies, Sociétés, Civilisations, 1971 May
    - "Plato's Myth Of The Statesman, the Ambiguities of the Golden Age and of History", offprint from The Journal Of Hellenic Studies, 1978
    - "La Société platonicienne des dialogues", offprint from Aux origines de l'héllenisme, 1984
    - "Thèses sur le révisionnisme" offprint from L'Allemagne nazie et le génocide juif, 1985
- Other printed items, 1938-79; Series III; 0.2; (1 box)
  - Books Abroad [journal], 1952 Spring (Box 3, Folder 48)
    Inscribed by Joseph Prescott
  - La Corée du Sud [journal], 1978 (Box 3, Folder 49)
    also includes: letter from "Susan" to Maria Jolas, 1978 Jun 3
  - Etudes de Lettres [journal], 1938 Oct 1 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Catalog of exhibition at the National Institute of Arts and Letters: Louis Bouché, Adolf Dehn, Marcel Duchamp, Ben Shahn, 1970
    - also includes: letter by "S. S." [Stella Seidenmann?] to Maria Jolas, 1970 May 5 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Quatre Vents [journal], 1946 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Senn, Fritz, James Joyce Pub Zürich [booklet], 1979 (Box 3, Folder 53)
    inscribed by the author
  - Temple, Ruth Z., Nathalie Sarraute, Columbia University Press [booklet], 1968 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Photograph of Lucia Joyce's grave, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Invitation to lecture "Les Années Vingt" at the Centre culturel américain, 1959 Mar 16 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - Clipping: "Les souvenirs de Sylvia Beach", 1959 (Box 3, Folder 57)